Morning.
Morning. How is everybody?
Good, thank you.
Do you want to be there? You can have that seat.
Right. So,
we had you in a year or two ago.
Yeah.
Slightly longer, I think.
It was-
Yeah.
Yeah, a couple of years ago, I think.
Yep.
Mm.
And we're just, I guess, looking for an update on how it's going.
Mm-hmm.
So, I'll leave it in your capable hands.
Yeah. It, uh, it is-
Oh, okay.
Shut that down.
That's perfect.
So first off, thank you for the opportunity to come back and give you an update.
For those that I haven't met, so I'm Suzy Keeling, head of science research at Beef
and Lamb New Zealand, and I'll let Cara introduce herself.
Yeah. Cara Brosnahan, principal scientist, animal health research at Beef and Lamb
as well.
And so what we thought we would do today, rather than talk, I guess, and sort
of, yeah, skim across the details of all the different components of the facial
eczema program, is that we would talk to you about what has
become affectionately known as the Sheep Poo study, which is the
epidemiological study, where we have looked to get a better understanding of the
prevalence and distribution of facial eczema across New Zealand.
So we'll spend a little bit of time on that, and certainly, if you're curious about
other parts of the program, by all means, we'd love to hear the questions.
For those of you that aren't familiar with facial eczema, so it's been in New
Zealand for, I guess, documented well over 120 years now.
There isn't a cure. Historically, it was thought of as
a
sorry, excuse me, North Island,
predominantly, disease. But certainly based on recent
years and evidence that we now have to date, it is spreading south,
and Cara will talk more about where we've actually found evidence of facial
eczema. I guess the other thing to
note is it is caused by a toxin known
as sporidesmin, which is produced by a fungus that essentially lives on
pasture. So that and the other, I guess, interesting
aspect when we think about other diseases, is facial eczema
isn't particularly--
it doesn't discriminate. So it does impact all ruminant
species. And in the New Zealand context, it is certainly one of our
most predominant endemic diseases.
But through the research that we have been doing, it is very obvious that it
is in other parts of the world. So that has actually offered the program
opportunities for international collaboration as well.
So I'll probably hand over to Cara now. If we can have the next slide.
Yeah, to talk us through. Yeah, go for it.
Oh, good.
So one of the first things that I wanted to cover
is that we've had a significant discovery in the first part
of the program, understanding more about the fungus itself.
So as you can see there, those are those little grenades that people look
for down the microscope to know how many spores are there, and that determines the
risk
of winter and actual facial eczema management.
So this was always thought of as one species of fungus.
But actually, when we looked at the DNA, there are two species of fungus that
look identical down the microscope.
One can produce the toxin that causes FE, and one actually
doesn't have the mechanisms to be able to do that.
So it's really important to know that these two are there, and that we can
distinguish them, so that we can create better tools that are
definitely for that toxin producing fungus.
But also so that we can assess the risk better and more accurately
for farmers. So we have a test that we've developed in the
program as well, a PCR test, to distinguish these two.
And now we're in the stages of validating that
for a commercial use, and part of that is actually understanding what the
interpretation of that result means, 'cause it's all very well having a test.
But if farmers and vets don't know how to interpret it, then yeah, it's kind of
useless. So that's where we're at with that. So that's a very exciting discovery.
And next slide, please.
And it was quite cool to actually name it toxicarius.
Oh, yeah. That's-
Yeah, that's-
Sorry, I didn't-
Yeah.
So the long name for the toxin producing one is Pseudopithomyces toxicarius, and
then the other one-
Cara's really good at saying that quickly.
And then the other one that's the non-toxic species is the Pseudopithomyces
charterii, which is the previous name for what it was
always called. So it is a little bit confusing, but given that it's toxicarius, we
feel like it's a little bit easier for people to know which one's the toxin
producing one.
And the other
major piece of work in this program is getting farmers involved.
So for the last three years, we've had an epidemiological study
running to understand the distribution and prevalence of facial
eczema in New Zealand. So not just where we assume it to be, but actually taking
samples from across the country so that we know.
We've had really amazing participation throughout the three years.
So in season one, just over 200 farmers, and then by season three,
up to almost 300 farmers. So this is-- It's very hard to
get people participating voluntarily, and the fact that it grew over time
is, yeah, just a kind of reminder of how important this disease is
for New Zealand farmers.
So next slide, please. So this is, yeah, the Sheep
Poo study, because we did get farmers to send in sheep poo from a
mob of sheep every two weeks from October to May for three years.
So it was a huge effort.
Wow.
They did get results back,
as soon as we got the results from the lab, so they were informed of their
risk as well, but still a huge effort.
How many farmers, sorry? How many farmers?
So in year one, there was just over 200.
Wow.
And year three, almost 300 farmers.
So over the whole study, there were over 400 farmers participating.
So
I think there was about 150 farmers that stayed for the whole three years.
Hmm.
And then that changed in terms of the numbers and people for the rest of the
time. So yeah
Pretty impressive, yeah.
So if you can... Sorry, there are a couple of...
Yeah, if you click one more.
So the other thing is this is a massive data set that we
now have that we can dig into for other purposes, and the
largest data set on FE, I'm going to say in the world, because no one else is
looking at it as intensely as us.
And yeah, over 30,000 records so far, and
that's not including season three.
So we think we'll get about up to 50,000 data points, which is
massive. And
the other thing about it is that it was longitudinal, so it's over those three
years. And because FE is so variable year to year, it's really important to
get that spread and not just focus on one year.
So it was that each farmer had the same mob of sheep they were following or?
Each year they could do a different mob, but within the
year it was the same mob, so that we could trace it around the farm and see
what paddocks were at risk and what weren't.
It also gave us a really big bank of samples to be able to test that
toxic versus non-toxic strain. So we're working through those to understand where
the different species are around New Zealand, if they are, in fact, different in
different parts of the country.
So we'll get a lot more information there.
And the other thing is fecal facial eczema
spore counts aren't a routine diagnostic that farmers use,
so it provides more information to be able to interpret results if they
do want to use it, because it does give you a little bit different information than
a pasture spore count because it's telling you what the animal is actually eating,
so what the risk is to the animal rather than what the potential risk is.
So there's a little bit different there.
Great. Next slide, please.
So we did find that it's certainly not a North Island problem.
So this is a snapshot of over the three
years-
We're in the red zone
... where,
yeah. What zone are people in?
So this is the highest spore count that was seen within
that region over each year.
This is red, babe.
Over each year.
Oh, there you go.
Yeah. I'll talk you through. So green means there were no spores seen in
that region,
and then up to black, which is the very dangerous.
So the maroony red is that moderate risk
range, and then the yellow to orange is lower
risk, but if you're continually eating those spores, there still is the risk
of getting facial eczema.
But it's getting worse, what, just in totality it looks like?
Well, it's just very variable between the seasons.
Okay.
So that-
Just hot and wet, isn't it?
Yeah.
So you can see on the-
Exactly
... East Coast, obviously in '23, '24, it was hot and wet.
Yes.
Mm.
And then it's traditionally the West Coast.
Yeah. So it's a really important reminder that it's not going to be the same every
season, which is why monitoring is so key.
And yeah, found spores down in Southland in the first year.
We didn't see them in year two and three, but we did see them in
Otago throughout the three years.
West Coast, little bit of a caveat on that one.
The first two years we could not get West Coast farmers to to join.
Oh, okay.
So there was only a couple.
Yeah.
And the third year we had a colleague that was involved with
the Sheep Coast Study who lives on the West Coast, so she encouraged a lot more
farmers into the study, and we got a more realistic picture of what it looks like
there, because they definitely do get facial eczema and clinical facial eczema.
Not as many sheep on the coast either, is there?
No.
But it is wet, so.
Yeah, exactly.
That's a factor.
And
the dairy cattle there, they've definitely been having problems the last few years.
Mm.
Yeah. And so clinical outbreaks, yeah, West Coast,
Nelson, Marlborough, Tasman, north essentially in every region.
So first year there was about 12% of the farmers
participating that reported clinical FE.
Second and third year, almost 30% of the farmers reported clinical
FE. So there's still a lot happening out there.
Mm.
Um-
So, can you... What's the difference between the spore count in the
grass and the fecal count? Like, is it-
So it is, so the pasture-
But what's the advantage of doing one or the other?
So the pasture spore count is good to understand when those spores are
rising.
Yeah. So that's traditionally what people have done.
That's traditionally what people use.
Yeah, that's what we've done.
Yeah. And it's a really good indicator.
So what we've noticed within the study is that those pasture spore counts and
fecal spore counts can be quite different because it depends where the animals are
grazing. So they might not actually be grazing down into that
area that you're collecting the pasture spore, the pasture from.
But also we've noticed that the pasture spore count can be quite low
and the fecal spore count can be quite high.
So they're grazing in areas that you're not necessarily picking your pasture from.
So it does become a little bit more complex, but the good thing is with
all this data, we'll be able to... That's one of the goals is to analyze it and
understand where is best to use each of the diagnostic tools.
So is it actually useful to use fecal spore counts at certain
times versus pasture, or should you be doing both to give you a better picture?
So that's something we're working through, because we do think it's a really useful
tool to understand where
animals are actually eating the spores.
And what about pasture management? Does that have an influence at all?
Because if you don't graze so low.
Yes. Yeah, definitely.
So are you measuring that too? Are you measuring that too?
Yes. So we've been asking farmers who are submitting samples
how, like what their pasture height is.
Yeah.
And what we've seen in the first two years is that if you're above five
centimeters, you're much safer.
Yeah.
Below five centimeters-
So it's when they get down to the bottom.
Yes.
Yeah.
So similar to internal parasites, they're all sitting in that bottom layer.
So if you're not going down and grazing that hard, then you
are reducing the risk.
But often in summer you're short of grass too.
Exactly.
Yeah.
So sometimes it's not an option.
But knowing that that is a risk and then putting other management in places
is important.
Mm-hmm.
Yeah.
Did you look at why 2024 and 2025 have bigger no
spore area? Because spores would survive for at least
If, I mean, the standard, like three, four months.
Yeah, spores are very hardy.
Yeah.
Yep.
Yeah. So how did it happen, like 2024, 2025
has bigger no spores area? And then,
yeah, so w- what-
So it's likely that, we're still analyzing the data, but it's likely to
do with those weather patterns.
Mm.
So the spores might be there, but at low levels and
that fungi isn't actively growing and producing more spores
potentially.
Mm.
So they, yeah.
You're right, that they will still be there waiting for that environment so that
they can grow again. Yeah. Yeah. And we've also got a side project,
looking at what are those environmental triggers of sporogenesis production as
well. Mm. Because as Cara said, when we started this work, we didn't have the new
diagnostic tool that separates toxic from non-toxic. Mm.
So this picture represents a combined, the good
and the bad fungus. But then we've also got other work that's going on,
which is helping us understand what those environmental triggers of the
toxin are. Because even if we detect by DNA that the toxic
fungi is there, it doesn't necessarily mean that it's actively producing- Mm ...
the toxin. Because part of, I guess, the complexity of this is
we don't really know why it's advantageous for this
fungus to produce the toxin in the environment.
Like its end goal was never about harming animals. Mm.
So why is it advantageous for this fungus
that lives down in a particular part of the pasture?
Like is it so it
can kill other microbes, so it can out-compete them?
So all of that isn't quite clear. Mm-hmm.
Yeah. You mentioned about you developing that PCR test.
Mm-hmm.
I
don't imagine it's unique to New Zealand. Is it?
The fungus?
Yeah.
No.
Yeah, so that test not developed anywhere else?
No, because a lot of other places in the world
are, it's not as bad as New Zealand.
So New Zealand definitely
has, I guess, the worst cases of facial eczema.
Mm.
But it is popping up more and more around the world.
So Netherlands in 2019 had their first case reported of facial
eczema. There's been a few reports in the literature in the last few years
from Portugal.
Mm.
Spain. Yeah.
How do we compare with Australia?
Yeah, so Australia, it's very confined to an area in
Victoria and mainly in dairy.
So yeah. I think probably South Africa would be- Yeah ...
the country that might be second to us in terms of their issues.
But once again, challenge for dairy animals. Yeah. Mm.
So that's like a good opportunity that we have a test now.
Yes.
Yeah.
Yeah, and I think that is why this program is so important because
it will become-
Yeah
... more and more around the world.
If it gets widely accepted, yeah.
Yeah. And people will be looking to us-
Yeah
... for solutions. That's really good. Yeah.
Because we've been quite proactive in building an international network.
Yeah.
Not only understanding what their challenges are, but sharing our
insights. Because if the longer term outcome is that we can minimize
harm to animals globally because we can share what we learn here, then
that is certainly highly beneficial. Mm.
Exactly.
Yeah.
Well, very important.
Next slide. So the other thing was that the season was
longer than we anticipated. So this is just a snapshot
from this previous year from February to June.
So often, people stop sampling kind of
April, May. But when we continued it out, there was still quite a few
regions that had high spore counts in June.
So it's just something to be aware of, of not making those assumptions that, yes,
it starts here, it finishes here. Every season's gonna be different.
And to continue monitoring when you're thinking about stopping any
management.
And-
You went in between Cs.
Did you- Yeah. Did you talk... Oh, no, it's terrible, isn't it?
November.
But did you look into, because I know that it can lay dor- it may not
show in animals. Mm-hmm. But we lamb in
June. Yeah. And then sometimes it's dormant, and then it comes up when the animals
are under stress after they've had a lamb. Yes.
So it can actually present in the symptoms- Later, yes ...
can present in July or August. Yeah.
And that is
usually because, as you say, because- But you may not have noticed it earlier.
Yeah, exactly. Yeah. The liver was under such pressure, and it was fine under
normal circumstance. Yeah. But then with the pressure of- Yes, the baby. Yeah ...
lambing or anything, yep, definitely.
So that delayed facial eczema is certainly an issue.
Yeah. And that's why that subclinical FE-
Oh, yeah ... is so important and not well,
like we all know that figure of if you have one clinical
animal, you're likely to have 10 subclinical.
But it's not often registered how important that is, because that
is lost production, as you say, that can affect the animal later in life when
they're under other stress. And throughout the life of the animal, that is reduced
productivity. So getting a better handle on what individual farmers'
subclinical FE might be is really important.
So we've had, um- They don't transfer it to their lamb, do they? No. No. Yeah.
It's just them. No. It's more, yeah, it's more that because they are so much under
pressure
through that lambing, then that's when it all comes out.
Yeah, so within the SheepCo study, we've had a group of farmers who are monitoring
more intensely,
and that's blood samples, fecal samples, pasture.
And so we've got more up-to-date numbers of what that
subclinical impact is looking like.
So once we analyze all the data, we'll be able to have some more information on
that.
And I think, yeah, the only other thing I
wanted to mention about the SheepCo study, so all of the data, we're using
that to build a predictive model for FE.
So it's using real data as well as 30 years of meteorological
data and machine learning so that we're not
biasing what we think the parameters might be that affect FE.
We're letting the models run, and that will give a much clearer
picture of what are those things that drive FE long
term. So that's pretty exciting work.
The two years of the data and the Where
the data is showing that it's looking really good, and then the intention is to
test it on year three's data, and then have something available
for beta testing for farmers this coming FE season.
So there's lots of very exciting things coming out of it.
I think that's all I have.
Yeah. Let's go to the next slide.
Yeah, pop all of them up. Great. Thank you.
So I guess one of the things on reflection, as Cara mentioned
at the beginning, we
had high hopes about farmer participation, but we certainly didn't
think that was going to be as successful as it was.
So
that in itself, of setting the foundations for farmers to then start their own
kind of management and monitoring going forward, and we've built that
community. There's a WhatsApp group.
There are farmers participating in webinars.
So it's gone from being something that perhaps you didn't want to necessarily
talk about openly, to starting to create that dialogue.
And it's also been the dialogue that we've started to build with the veterinary
community as well. So one of the things that the program is doing is,
has built a continuous professional development course for
veterinarians, and so we've partnered with the New Zealand Veterinary Association
for that. So that's going to be launched in the next six months, I think.
Yep.
And probably the big thing that I think we've still got a
challenge going forward is that awareness and myth-busting.
So there, we spoke initially about the historic
perspective that it's only a North Island problem.
We've now got really solid evidence that it is a South Island problem.
Mm.
So from the perspective of starting to have conversations with farmers in the South
Island about what does preparedness look like, what does introducing FA-tolerant
genetics look like?
That now that narrative around that when you look under the microscope, you're
actually looking at two different fungi.
One is the problem child, one is completely harmless.
So how does that inform real-time risk alerts?
So the predictive model that Cara has spoken about, once
that's launched, farmers will actually be able to assess what their own
potential risk is for that season.
The other insights that we've gathered, because we do an end of season
survey from everybody that's participated in the sheep poo study,
is because they were measuring and monitoring, it gave them the ability to make
management decisions like zinc earlier rather than
later. But also because they kept monitoring, they were able to stop zinc
sooner. So starting to show the power of actually
collecting that evidence for your own farm.
Spotting hidden losses, so certainly to that educational piece and creating
awareness about subclinical disease and what to look out for,
the importance of that.
And the big achievement for us, as I've already mentioned, is the
trust and the partnership that we've been able to form with farmers.
It's just been so exciting to get the feedback,
have the participation. It's a pretty substantial commitment, you're going
out every fortnight, collecting information about your animals,
measuring pasture, sending in the sheep poo samples,
all of those. But having that real sense of ownership and participation in the
program has just been so exciting.
I still get very passionate about it.
And we can go to the final slide, or we can wrap up.
So you've probably got the sense that Beef and Lamb is certainly not doing this
alone. It is a genuine cross-sector collaboration, not only with our
farmers, but also MPI as significant co-funders.
And then we have a number of research providers in New Zealand
and Australia, but also quite an extensive number of
in-kind partners as well. So we're coming at this
problem with a very multidimensional view.
We do know that the solutions that the program needs to deliver
have to be farm systems based. There's not going to be a silver
bullet for this challenge. So it is going to be about the animal
component, the pasture component, people, the environment,
and how that's all packaged together.
And we're just over halfway, and with yeah, about another...
We end December 2030.
Yep.
Right, we'll go to questions. Suz?
A couple of questions. So one, how are you transferring this
information down to the actual farmers-
Mm-hmm
... or sharing the information to the farmers? And also, what's the end game?
What are you trying to achieve? Are you trying to reduce facial eczema?
Are you trying to find a cure or a spray or something?
Or you, I don't know, what's the
end game? You say that there's no cure.
Yeah.
And so or are you just, is it about or is it simply about awareness?
Because I'd say most farmers are well aware.
Certainly people that are-
No, it's definitely going further than awareness.
Right.
But I guess to your first question in terms of how we disseminate and
create understanding of facial eczema.
So you've got your more traditional channels of, I guess, like fact
sheets and webinars and
workshops, but-
How's the engagement on there? Pretty good?
Do you want to talk about those ones in terms of...
Because I guess we've also taken this as an opportunity to design-
Answer Bruce's questions.
Yeah. Design-
Yeah.
... the facial eczema workshops
that we have done, we've done them differently.
And they've been really successful in that they have had a
combined,
so you've got an expert panel.
You'll also have expert farmer panel talking about their experiences of
facial eczema. We also typically
include, I guess if you like, it's more of a hands-on applied,
so actually looking like postmortems.
So opening up the animal and looking at what a potential liver could look
like that's been impacted. So the workshops are
designed to create for all different stages of learning and
learning preferences as well. So they have been incredibly
useful. But the real success of those workshops is creating
light bulb moments that when you see what a liver
inside a sheep looks like, you then think, "Okay, well, when I'm going to
maybe, you know-" ... cull some animals for dog tucker,
I'm then going to stop and have a look at my own animals themselves.
So it's starting to create more of that applied learning rather than just
theoretical learning. And certainly in the webinars that we've been doing, they're
very farmer focused. They're not science heavy, but it's also about
showing farmers that because of all of this new information, this is now what you
can do. So to the second part of your
question,
it's going to have to be about how we can optimize the farm system
and have more effective multi-pronged management things
that essentially set you up to minimize the risk and ultimately the impact
of facial eczema. Yeah.
Well, that's because it's-
Yeah
... like it's amazing that you've got such a great sample of people that have,
as you said, the best in the world or whatever it is.
Yeah.
But,
so have you determined through that process that there are
management tools you can make to minimize the effects?
Yeah.
So is that part of it? Like so you-
Yes.
There's certain things you can do other than not grazing so low, but once the
animals have been diagnosed, or you can see symptoms of it in your
stock.
Yeah.
Are there certain things you can do to make it better?
Yeah, so I think probably, jump in here, Caroline, with stuff that
I've missed. I think we're probably more in the
preventative management space at the moment.
Right.
In terms of
the program having capacity to look for, let's say, treatments.
Like once you've got evidence of facial eczema in your stock, currently there
isn't anything on offer.
No.
In terms of like a treatment or something that you could give them.
Oh, no, I don't necessarily mean it.
Is that what you mean? No.
I don't necessarily mean a drench or anything.
I mean like, are there certain ways you can manage them?
Like do you put them on long grass or keep them in the shade or through-
Yeah
... or keep them in the sun or whatever?
Yeah. Supportive, yeah.
Yeah.
Yeah. Supportive actions. Yeah.
And-
No. Oh, that's brilliant. Thank you.
Yeah.
Thank you very much.
Very interesting.
Are there any
brass species being bred that may be resistant to the fungus in
the first place?
There isn't at the moment,
but we do know that there are certain forages that are much lower risk,
and they just can't grow on them. So one of-
Brassicas?
Yeah. Brassicas, chicory.
So one of the parts of the program is,
yeah, I guess because s- since zinc came out, there was a lot of work done
on pastures and before zinc came out.
Yes.
And then everyone kind of forgot about that, and we were like, "Oh, well, let's
just move to zinc," because it's
Easier
... easy. So it's part of this is also bringing back
that knowledge about the pastures, making sure that is up to date, and then
creating more resources and case studies of where farmers have applied
them in a farm system to make them work, and to make them work
maybe for internal parasites as well.
So you're not just doing it for facial eczema, but you might also be doing it to
break the cycle of parasites. So yeah, there's definitely that part of the
program as well. So we've got some seed companies, as you'll see, as in-kind
partners, so they are helping us out with
that. But I guess another part of the program as well,
there's been a lot of anecdotal evidence that farmers say once they
change their, soil health and pasture management, they don't seem to get
facial eczema as much. So we are looking into a proof of
concept just to see if we can get some data around that and see if that is real.
And then that might progress into something, but we really need some data
first before going in there.
Lucy, can I just hop on there? Are you working with companies like Holter in terms
of some of their pasture management stuff?
Like just-
Yeah. So we have-
I don't know if you want to-
Yeah, so we've-
Okay
... yeah, we've had conversations with them and also Cow Manager in terms of,
because the other part of the program is like looking at behavioral, like
early indicators of disease.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
So whether or not with their animal health data that they collect.
Mm.
But yeah, we do have, yeah, a, it's a work in progress-
Yeah
... in terms of, yeah, what, yeah, technology and wearables, yeah, could be used.
Yeah.
Yeah, because another, like for wearables and
a relatively easy part would be when farmers know what parts of their farm are hot
or certain gullies.
Exactly.
They can just restrict-
Exactly
... the animals going there.
Yeah.
But it is, it's also that behavior stuff.
But then it is, yeah, they can also,
yeah, totally use it a, as a kind of a high level.
Mm.
Yeah.
That's exciting.
Cool.
Yeah.
No, very good. Look, thank you very much for taking the time.
It's really interesting to see the progress you've made.
Yeah.
And,
I guess
we're out of questions for
the other areas, but,
I, I guess as a
economic impact that-
Mm-hmm
... FE does have around the country, and
there's not a lot known until, and the more we know, the better we
can manage it, I guess. So-
Yeah
... thanks very much.
No. Thank you.
Thank you.
Have a good day. Stay cool.